hello students myself nivedita karma day
the Faculty of Rao IIT Academy today
we'll be seeing the chapter one that is
of a hardware part microprocessor and
organization of a 8:08 five oh you will
be
in this chapter we will be seeing it the
most probably the concepts of the
microprocessor 8:08 five only so the
first topic of this chapter is that is
will be saying evaluation of
microprocessor which we call it as am
you P also over here so that means in
this evolution of a microprocessor there
are five generations are present so that
is the first generation second
generation third generation for this
generation and the last one is my fifth
generation same way as we see it in the
different subject that in the history
VCR we are seeing the evolution of the
how the human being is being generated
and all good things see when the
technical will be saying it the how my
microprocessor is being generated and
when it is being generated so over here
in the evolution of a microprocessor
that is the first generation that is my
first microprocessor was being launched
that is the 4 0 0 4 and this is being
launched by the Intel company so I will
be calling it as the Intel's
microprocessor for 0 0 4 which is having
a size of only and only a full bit that
is nothing but a one nibble so I can say
you to wear one bit nibble is equal to 4
bit away so that is in our generation if
I say
- the negligible for bid is nothing that
is we are we cannot save it a single
image was over here so that means 4-bit
microprocessor was being wrong so that
is in the year 1971 so what is the main
purpose of this that is the main purpose
of this was being utilized in the
calculators so that is microprocessor
for 0:04 which is having the size of the
four bit and this was being installed in
the internally in my calculators for
what purpose for doing my arithmetic and
logical operations so if I want to do
the perform where the if I want to do
the calculation of my addition
subtraction multiplication and division
so only this for calculations was being
possible in the microprocessor four zero
zero four then the next microprocessor
that advanced version of the four zero
zero four was being launched that is a
microprocessor I will be calling it as a
four zero four zero once again the size
is also same way via the 4-bit water and
this advanced enhanced feature was same
once again it is was being embedded in
the calculator that is the usage of over
here was calculators suppose if I am
inserting my five digit number into the
calculators so is it a possible thing
know why the reason is I am having only
a size of four bit so that means each
and every number that is each digit is
accommodating only a single bit so if
I'm inserting the fifth digit in the
calculator that will be possible right
now let me see that maximum sixteen
digit or a 15 digit in the current
generation we can store it inside the
calculator that is in my scientific
calculators also but over here that is
the very first microprocessor by witch's
Intel's company has launched it so this
was being used it only and only in the
calculators next now we'll be seeing the
next generation that is the second
generation of a microprocessor so in
this generation that is the updated
version which we have seen in the first
generation was a microprocessor
zero for then the updated it came sir
microprocessor for zero for zero that is
having a size of a four bit there is a
one level and this your second
generation in the 1974 the Intel company
has launched the microprocessor eight
zero eight zero that is in this eight
zero eight zero the sizes of her 8-bit
this is an enhanced version of the
microprocessor eight is zero zero eight
which was in the first generation then
in the same 1974 only one more
generation was being launched that is
sorry one more microprocessor was being
lost that is a MCD six eight zero zero
so that is this is nothing but my
motorola company has launched it this
microprocessor six eight zero zero next
once again the updated version was the
said eight zero microprocessor was lost
that is the Z log company has launched
at this micro processor then in the next
after two years in the 1976 the
microprocessor 8:08 v was being lost
which is we are starting it in the 12
standard which is having the size of
only and only 8 bit that means my size
is of only 1 byte over yup so micro
processor 8 0 8 5 is having the size of
8-bit in the 1977 im6 1 0 0 this
microprocessor was being launched and
with this t 8 1 9 0 this microprocessor
also being launched so that is T is
nothing but it is allocated for them
Toshiba company and I which is nothing
but my inter-cell company has launched
at this microprocessor accordingly that
is the initial company has launched at
the six one eight zero zero and the
Toshiba is launched at the D eight one
nine zero which is having the size of a
12 bit that means the updated version of
my micro processor 8 0 8 5 that is a 4
bit has got increase in this
microprocessor T as well as in the
inter-cell 6 1 0 0 so these are the
regarding about my second generation
list that is in the microprocessor 80-85
concept
is most public that is present in the
second generation which will be starting
it in the whole quell standard that is
in the step chapter one will be studying
it regarding 80-85 registers how flags
are getting affected multiple types of a
flags and their addressing modes and in
the second chapter 80-85 instruction
sets will which will be studying it
there is a total account of my
instruction set as sabaidee for the next
generation which will be saying it the
third generation so in the third
generation until company has launched at
microprocessor eight zero eight six that
is within the year my 1978 to 1980 then
this was being followed by this a lock
company also as well as the Motorola
company also that is this is a log 8 is
0 0 0 curve this microprocessor was
being lost and Motorola has launched a
six eight zero zero so this
microprocessor was being launched in the
year 1978 to 1980 and the size of this
microprocessor was a 16 bit that bits
that is nothing but my I'll be having
the size of 2 bytes itself that is in
the third generation my enhanced version
of my bag that is a microprocessor size
who's got enhanced that is a 16-bit
previously was a 12-bit that before that
it was a 8-bit before that the minimum
and the initial size was a 4 bit so that
is as you are seeing it slowly slowly my
microprocessor is getting enhanced in
few years so one more thing in the trial
generation that is my memory space was
that is a 64 kilobyte so that is other
features like full arithmetic execution
and efficient level of my higher
languages is getting addressing over you
so this is about like third generation
so the next generation is the fourth
generation of a micro Pro micro
processor so in this in the year 1980
when the Intel company has launched the
8 0 3 8 6 version that is before this
the micro processor 8 0 8 6 was being
launched that is the size of my micro
processor a 0
six was having a 16-bit so over here the
updated version of my eight zero eight
six was nothing but my eight zero two
eight six was there and later after my
eight zero two eight six that is this
eight zero three eight six version was
being then the next updated version over
a two zero three eight six the eight
zero four eight six was journalism later
on after the microprocessor zero four
eight six it came the Pentium 1 then the
Pentium 2 Pentium 3 Celeron series then
also these all the series was being
upgraded over them
so in the year 1981 with the help of the
micro until eight zero three eight six
one more microprocessor was being
launched that is the IE
px four three two then the next one that
is that HP company has run just HP how
do you do that is my Herb Ritts Packard
has launched it then the next series
came that is m6 8 0 to 0 that is the
once again motorola company has launched
at this series this is having a size of
32-bit microprocessor so this
microprocessor was being getting
introduced and last but not my least
that is a microprocessor here zero four
eight six microprocessor was being
rushed
once again the size of my four eights X
also was my 32-bit itself so this this
microprocessor is being used for it can
address my physical memory of my 4gb
data so these are my content about my
fourth generation now the last
generation is the fifth generation of
the microprocessor that is after the
Year 1993 this Intel Pentium
is being launched then the next Pentium
2 Pentium 3 so all this microprocessor
was being launched by my Intel company
that is the size of this Intel company
there is a sorry microprocessor size was
the 64 bit so that means until has made
the improvement in the microprocessor to
design to provide the greatest speed of
my microprocessor that it also radio it
also having the system can run on my new
operating system
like my unix linux ubuntu etc so one
more thing is then that is this
processor in this generation we call it
as the term pentium and this after 1996
the next microprocessor was being
launched that is a seller on xenon DX
for i 3 and the i7 so shuuran's always
keep it in mind that is whatever is
being specified in the textbook that
microprocessor only you have to
specified on the paper also and one more
thing this microprocessor is also having
the sizes of a 64 bit only and this
microprocessor is being most probably
supporting for my land whatever the
server connection is there
whatever my possibility of my internet
connection that is the upgraded version
if I see it with my 4 generation or the
third generation whatever my land
supporting is it is being supporting for
my mod I'm at all
so all this possibility was being
upgraded because of this microprocessor
that is most probably the priority goes
from the Pentium onwards so these were
the regarding of my evolution of a
microprocessor now we'll be seeing the
next concept that is the register
registers so the thing is what do you
mean by a register that is in the
microprocessor register is nothing but
some you are storing the value or a data
that is nothing but my register where
you so that means any sort of a data I
want to store it I will be storing it in
the register only one more thing
resistors is a different thing which we
are using it in the physics concept in
the physical physics keyword over them
and this is the computer keyword that it
does a register so register is which is
having which is being used for storing
the data now in this register there are
multiple types that is a b c d e h n
that means over here a is nothing but my
accumulator which is having the size of
a 8-bit over here next same
and see these are the individual
resistors which is having the size of
eight 8-bit daughters it's in every
register is having the size of a 1 by
the way M so now and this first one is a
accumulator so what is the main purpose
of a accumulator is which is being used
for storing the result the result of our
thematical and logical operation so most
probably the accumulator will be storing
the result of arithmetical and logical
operations so next B and C that is else
combination I will be calling it as the
term pair B over here next de register
in the combination I will be calling it
as a term pair D and next one I will be
calling it as a it's el perro via not
only simply its fell so over in the B
register it will be having the size of
only 8-bit content so suppose if I am
showing a nine nine digit data that
won't be possible and in the B register
CV in all the register so the maximum
content of my register size is only a
ditch not beyond that so we have B and C
in the combination I will be calling it
as a pair B so obviously my size will be
getting increased that is my size is
getting of a 16-bit away that is walking
but my to buy it edita same way if I
can't get carrying for getting carry
forwarded toward my de once again I will
be calling it as the term parity which
is having the size of a 16-bit data next
Etzel pair no doubt HL pair is also of
my 16-bit that learns I can see itself
pair equal to memory that is I denote
the memory as a term M for the whole
year
you have to keep it in mind that is
Excel there is nothing but my memory
memory is nothing but my itself a always
key you have to keep it in mind but
don't get confused that where whenever I
have to use a memory I can use it H also
or I can use it m not like that in the
programming language wherever for the
particular syntax that is for the
particular instructions it's required at
that time only I have to use it for
their children Lea and for the memory I
have to use it f so it's short like that
that if a memory is correlated that
means I can use it H by H cell pair also
or I can use it for the M also next that
is HL pair mode out it will be storing a
16-bit content that is my address will
be storing it in the itself pair now
next one is the temporary register no
doubt this is also having the sizer for
8-bit that is temporary register as the
name says my value will be getting
stored as a temporary storage also
temporary storage only that means I can
store the data for the temporary purpose
only save me in this e+ bliss now what
we have seen the content that is where
my data is getting stored I am showing
the data in my variables so is there any
composition that I can use it only five
variables or I can use it only ten
variables as the C++ program no that
means there is a no limitation of a
variable in the C++ programming I can
use it any variables in which I wanted
but over here in this scenario is not
like that the variable is locked emitter
resistor wire in the microprocessor dat
files so that means we're only a
selectively registers are present that
means for storing the value I will be
accommodating or I'll be utilizing it
only this five registers only so any
sort of a combination will be there so
there is a specific size only and
specific number of my register which I
have to use it again and again in the
whole program of my 80-85 so they say in
which we have done the swapping of two
numbers
program in the C++ there is a void
swapping of two numbers I use a
temporary variable same way where your
this temporary register is acting as a
temporary variable now one more thing is
that that is nothing but my a which is
having the size of an 8-bit that is
nothing but my flag very very important
register so that means flag register
what do you mean by a flag register flag
is nothing but I will be calling it as a
status register now the thing is what do
you mean vesti it is register so status
register means this flag which is
specifying that when my flag is getting
set and when my flag is getting reset so
that is writing over here that is when
my flag is getting set and when my flag
is getting reset so that is set means my
value that is my flag is getting flip or
my side is getting flop which is set is
nothing but my value will be one and
flop that is reset my value will be
getting 0 so that means when my flag is
getting settled when my when my flag is
having the value 1 that means my flag is
getting set and if my value content of
any sort of a fly which is having a 0
that means my fried is getting reset so
there are 5 types of a flag in this F
register that is a sign flag zero flag
auxilary carry flag parity flag and the
last one is the carry flag
so all this flight is having the size of
a 8-bit only and this flag which will be
specifying it that when this flags are
getting set that is my SERP and when my
is getting ve set that is one man
getting in this flow so this is about
the content of my flag resistor which we
call it as at all status register
william next one more is that that is pc
and SP i will be calling it that is
nothing but my stack pointer
and my program counter
so start pointer the thing is what do
you mean by a start pointer now in the
stack pointer suppose my value is having
the six value so that six value
obviously it will be storing it in the
computer in any sort of address so what
the stack pointer is doing it aware that
a stack pointer will be showing the
address of my current data
so suppose example my six where it is
getting stored that is a taking example
is C 0 2 to H that is a hexadecimal
value so that means it will be
specifying the memory location that is
in the C 0 to do by values pressure so
stack pointer will be showing my current
address of my data while the program on
program counter which will be showing
the current address incremented by 1
that means stack pointer plus 1 it will
be showing it in the program counter
that means suppose an example that is my
stack pointer which is so showing that
which is displaying the contents that is
a memory location as a c 0 to 2 so
program counter it will be specifying me
as a c 0 to 3 x so these are the
registers which you have to use it in
the microprocessor 80-85 and one more
thing
very very important that is from be till
SP or I can say e till the facts lab
also that is in short excluding
accumulator these mine
registers will be known as a general
purpose register so in the board's the
question is being asked that is defined
the term general purpose register so you
have to specify that excluding the
accumulator whatever my registers are
there that comes under my general
purpose register and put out what about
my accumulator that is accumulator is
most probably it is being accommodated
for storing the or storing the result
that is of my
article and logical operation so these
are the concepts which are about my
registers and my general purpose
register and in the general purpose
register one more is very very important
that is my F flag which is nothing but
my flag flag that is being used as a
status register